Guide to The Nation Institute Oral History Collection on Alger Hiss TAM.709
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Novick, Tillie, 2002 September 6; cuid174
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on September 6, 2002. In this interview Tillie Novick talks about her professional relationship with Alger Hiss, who worked as salesman for her printing company. She begins the interview by talking about her upbringing and discussing her husband's printing business, Novick and Son. She talks about meeting Hiss when he came to work for their company in 1958 and discusses her impressions of him as a person and an employee. She also discusses serving as a character witness for Hiss during his application for readmittance to the Massachusetts bar. She touches on Hiss's reaction to the news of Richard Nixon's impeachment and generally discusses the printing business between the 1950s and 1970s.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 174)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Papachristou, Alexander, 2001 October 23; cuid175
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on October 23, 2001. In this interview Alexander Papachristou discusses his friendship with Alger Hiss. He explains that Hiss was a friend of his parents, and took an interest in Papachristou because he was a student at Harvard Law School. He talks about how he later started working for Hiss's lawyers on a petition to reopen his case. Papchristou reflects on Hiss's sense of history, and his political beliefs. He also talks about moving to the Soviet Union and assisting Hiss during his search for archival materials related to his case. He talks about Russian historian Dimitri Volkoganov's statement about the lack of evidence against Hiss, and finishes the interview by discussing his personal beliefs about Hiss's innocence.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_14
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 175)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Papachristou, Judy, 2001 June 6; cuid176
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on June 6, 2001. In this interview Judy Papachristou talks about her friendship with Alger Hiss. She describes meeting Hiss and his wife Isabel in the 1970s. She explains that they were neighbors in East Hampton and would frequently have dinner parties together. The interview primarily focuses on Papachristou's memories of her social relationship with Hiss and focuses on their discussions about politics, the Cold War, and the United States judicial system.
  Electronic hum pulsates throughout recording
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 176)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Penn, Arthur, 2001 April 4; cuid177
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 4, 2001. In this interview Arthur Penn talks about his friendship with Alger Hiss. The interview begins with a discussion about public perceptions of Hiss's guilt or innocence in the decades following his conviction. Penn also discusses his social relationship with Hiss, and shares stories about Hiss and his second wife Isabel. In the interview Penn reflects on how the case against Hiss affected his life and speculates about the path Hiss's career may have taken had he not been accused of espionage.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_15
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Folder 177)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Penn, Peggy and Arthur, 2001 September 10; cuid178
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on September 10, 2001. In this interview Peggy and Arthur Penn discuss their close friendship with Alger Hiss. The first part of the interview focuses on discussions of Hiss's mental health and describes an episode where they helped Hiss after he was hospitalized in California. Much of the interview focuses on Hiss's relationship with his second wife Isabel, and includes a discussion about their decision to get married following the death of Hiss's first wife Priscilla. The end of the interview focuses on Hiss's physical decline toward the end of his life, and includes some personal stories about how they helped him during those years.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_16
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Folder 178)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Piel, Gerard, 2001 November 28; cuid179
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on November 28, 2001. In this interview Gerard Piel talks about his acquaintance with Alger Hiss and his opinions about the Hiss-Chambers case. Piel begins the interview by explaining that he met Hiss through some mutual friends a short time after he had been released from prison. Piel, who was the publisher of the magazine Scientific American, talks briefly about Hiss's intellectual interests and political beliefs. He describes Hiss as taking a "detached or historian's view of the world" and portrays his view of his years in prison as equally reflective. The end of the interview focuses on Hiss's work at the United Nation, and includes a brief discussion about the character of Whittaker Chambers.
  Muted sound with off-and-on electronic hum can be heard
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 6, 8)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 179)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Pike, Reverend Dr. Thomas, 2001 August 28; cuid180
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on August 28, 2001. In this interview Reverend Dr. Thomas Pike talks about Alger Hiss's spiritual beliefs and connection to his church. Pike was the reverend at the Episcopal church in Alger Hiss's neighborhood and talks about Hiss's attendance over the years. Pike explains that Hiss originally began attending the church when he was married to his first wife Priscilla. Pike talks about his personal relationship with many members of the Hiss family including Priscilla, Tony, Alger and Isabel, all of whom he saw at the church on an individual basis. Pike talks generally about Hiss's interest in the church and his spirituality.
  Electronic hum off-and-on throughout recording
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_17
  - Original Recordings (Box 3, Cassette 180)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Rabinowitz, Victor, 2001 March 30; cuid181
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on March 30, 2001. In this interview Victor Rabinowitz talks about his work on the 1979 petition for the writ of coram nobis filed by Alger Hiss's legal team an attempt to obtain a new trial. Much of the interview focuses on the work of Hiss's attorneys, and their use of FBI documents they obtained through Freedom of Information Act requests. He also touches on the work of Jeff Kisseloff who worked as a researcher for the legal team. Toward the end of the interview Rabinowitz speaks generally about Hiss's personality and his range of interests.
  Muted sound and constant "glitches" can be heard, as if recording was stopped and re-started
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_18
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 181)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Rafferty, Corinne and Dale Wiehoff, 2001 April 23; cuid182
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 23, 2001. In this interview Corrine Rafferty and Dale Wiehoff talk about their experiences as readers for Alger Hiss. The interview begins with Rafferty explaining that she began reading to Hiss through the suggestion of her friend Karen Brudney, and later invited her husband Dale Wiehoff to meet Hiss in 1985. The interviewees explain how they later became frequent dinner guests of Hiss and his wife. Much of the interview focuses on their perceptions of Hiss's personality and his literary interests. Wiehoff shares an anecdote about Hiss's recollections about the Agricultural Adjustment Act, and they both talk about Hiss's continued hope that he would someday be proven to be innocent.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_19
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 182)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Reuben, William, 2001 August 10; cuid183
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on August 10, 2001. In this interview William A. Reuben discusses his research on the Alger Hiss case and his acquaintance with Hiss. Reuben explains that he met Hiss in 1954 when he began research on a book about the Hiss-Chambers case. They later served as co-plaintiffs in a Freedom of Information Act lawsuit seeking to gain access to files related to his case. Reuben spends much of the interview discussing his research into Hiss's trial and talking about his impression of Whittaker Chambers. Reuben also talks about interviewing Max Bedacht and Sender Garlin, who Chambers had mentioned in his testimony to the FBI, and talks about how their recollections correspond with Chambers's account. He also shares his opinions about Hiss's attorney Claude Cross.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_20
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 183)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Rosenblum, Naomi and Walter, 2001 April 10; cuid184
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 10, 2001. In this interview Naomi and Walter Rosenblum talk about their friendship with Alger Hiss, whom they met in 1975. They begin by sharing a story about Hiss's close friendship with photographer Paul Strand. The bulk of the interview focuses on their social relationship with Hiss. They talk about Hiss's support of the New Deal and Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes, and discuss how he was affected by his prison experience. They also talk briefly about their mutual acquaintance Agnese Haury.
  Side 1 had muted/low volume
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_21
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 184)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Schane, Janet, 2001 August 28; cuid185
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on August 28, 2001. In this interview Janet Schane shares several personal anecdotes about Alger Hiss. Schane explains that she met Hiss through her friend Isabel Johnson, whom Hiss later married. She describes meeting Hiss sometime in the early 1960s, and tells a story about sharing a rental house in East Hampton with her husband Jesse Reid, Hiss, and Johnson. The bulk of interview focuses on a lengthy story about Hiss showing kindness to her mother who suffered from manic depression.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_22
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 185)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Schiffrin, Natalia, 2001 September 4; cuid186
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on September 4, 2001. In this interview Natalia Schriffin talks about how she helped Alger Hiss transcribe his memoir and later became one of his readers. Schriffin explains that she was recruited by Victor Navasky in the summer of 1985 to help Hiss transcribe his book Recollections of a Life, and after the book was finished began reading to him regularly. She talks about meeting the other young people who read for Hiss and her impression that he had a genuine interest in young people and their ideas. Much of the interview focuses on her perception of Hiss's personality. She also shares some stories about helping Hiss and his wife Isabel at their home.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 186)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Simon, Kenneth, undated; cuid187
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff. In this interview Kenneth Simon talks about working on Alger Hiss's legal team during his first appeal. In the interview Simon explains how he came to work for the Hiss defense team after graduating law school in the 1940s. The bulk of the interview focuses on the various tactics lawyers on the Hiss legal team pursued, and some of the disagreements between attorneys on his team. He also briefly discusses the role of Helen Buttenweiser in the Hiss cases. Toward the end of the interview he talks about Hiss after he was released from prison, his work selling stationery, and reflects on how the experience changed him.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 187)
- Spinak, Jane and Warren Scharf, 2001 June 7; cuid188
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on June 7, 2001. In this interview Jane Spinak and Warren Scharf talk about their friendship with Alger Hiss. Spinak explains that she met Hiss in the early 1980s through her friend Patricia Crown, and introduced him to Scharf several years later. They talk about living down the street from Hiss and in East Hampton, which made it easy for them to visit as readers. The bulk of the interview focuses on Spinak and Scharf's friendship with Hiss and his wife Isabel, the help they would give them around the house, and the lasting impression Alger had on them.
  Electronic hum can be heard throughout recording
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 188)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Tiger, Edith, 2001 April 19; cuid189
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 19, 2001. In this interview Edith Tiger describes her friendship with Alger Hiss. She explains that she met Hiss in 1968 when she was working at the National Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, and Hiss came into the office to sell stationery. She later came to know him more closely in 1976 after the passage of the Freedom of Information Act, when she assisted him with the coram nobis petition to overturn his conviction. She also talks about her friendship with his first wife Priscilla and his son Tony. The majority of the interview includes personal anecdotes including a story about Hiss befriending crime boss Frank Costello in prison, and another story about Hiss's relationship with Alan Weinstein, the author of Perjury: The HissChambers Case.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_23
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 189)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Train, Michael, 2001 March 23; cuid190
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on March 23, 2001. In this interview Michael Train talks about his experience reading for Alger Hiss. Train explains that he was recruited to read for Hiss sometime in the mid-1980s by their mutual friend Sally Belfrage. The interview focuses largely on Train's impressions of Hiss and his discussion of Hiss's reading interests. Train talks about his perception of Hiss as a very private person, and at the end of the interview he speculates about how history will remember him.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 190)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Tsitsera, Litsa, 2001 May 1; cuid191
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on May 1, 2001. In this short interview Litsa Tsitsera talks about her friendship with Alger Hiss. Tsitsera explains that she met Hiss at a party, and later began ordering stationery from him. She describes their relationship as largely social and talks about Hiss's interest in art and culture and shares a few stories about social gatherings with Hiss and his wife Isabel.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_24
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 191)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Von Mehren, Robert, 2001 April 20; cuid192
  This interview was conducted by Albert Ruben on April 20, 2001. In this interview Robert von Mehren talks about his acquaintance with Alger Hiss and the Hiss trials. He begins by explaining that he first met Hiss in 1948 when Whitney Debevoise, whose legal firm represented Hiss, asked for assistance on the libel suit against Whittaker Chambers. Von Mehren talks about advising Hiss's lawyers on responding to subpoenas from the House Un-American Activities Committee and the Grand Jury in New York, and offers his perspectives on the mistakes he believes were made by Hiss and his legal team during the libel suit and subsequent perjury trials. Von Mehren also shares his opinions about the personalities of Whittaker Chambers and Hiss.
  Side 1 of recording has muted audio
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Digital Transcript, TW_TAM_709_ER_25
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 192)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)
- Werchen, Raymond A., 2002 February 7; cuid194
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff on February 7, 2002. In this interview Raymond Werchen discusses his research on the Hiss legal cases. The bulk of the interview focuses on his analysis of the expert testimony regarding the typewriter that was introduced as evidence during Hiss's libel case against Whittaker Chambers. The bulk of the interview focuses on Werchen's reassessment of the expert testimony related to Hiss's typewriter. Werchen also shares his impressions of Hiss as a person and his thoughts about how his trials were handled by Hiss's lawyers.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 194A-B)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1-3)
- Wershba, Joseph and Shirley, 2002 March 7; cuid193
  This interview was conducted by Jeff Kisseloff. In this interview Joseph and Shirley Wershba talk about their friendship with Alger Hiss and media coverage of his trials. The Wershbas explain that they both worked at CBS in 1948 when the allegations against Hiss first surfaced, but note that they did not cover the story at the time. They talk about continued interest in Hiss's trials over the past decades, and discuss the research of Allen Weinstein, Victor Navasky, and John Lowenthal. They also talk about evidence related to the trials that came out over the years, citing Dimitri Volkoganov and the Venona papers. They also discuss the personality of Whittaker Chambers. The end of the interview focuses on their personal friendship with Hiss and the ways in which his life changed after the trials. They also talk generally about McCarthyism and the political climate contributed the investigation of Hiss.
  - Paper Transcript (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Cassette 193)
  - Access Copy (Box 5, Cd 1)